<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The History of self-defence, in requital to the history of passive obedience</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2138B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2456_CANCELLED</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14596</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13142546</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13142546</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98001</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43909)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98001)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 778:37 or 1702:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The History of self-defence, in requital to the history of passive obedience</title>
                  <author>Seller, Abednego, 1646?-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for D. Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Abednego Seller. Cf. Wing, NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>"The history of passive obedience since the reformation" was written by Abednego Seller.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed according to order."</note>
                  <note>This work appears at reel 778:37 as Wing S2456 (number cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.) and at reel 1702:14 as Wing H2138B.</note>
                  <note>Pages 32 and 33 misnumbered 17 and 28 respectively.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in Harvard University Library and Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Government, Resistance to.</term>
               <term>Obedience.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98001:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98001:1"/>
            <head>The Hiſtory of Self-Defence, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THere being nothing ſo natural to a Creature indued with life, as by all means poſſible to endeavour the perſerving of it, it may be juſtly matter of admiration to the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering part of the World, that ſome that ſeem to have improved their underſtandings many degrees beyond the reach of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Men in all manner of Knowledge, ſhould yet degenerate ſo far as to be more ſtupid than the Brutes themſelves, and not only endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to perſwade men out of their ſenſes, and render them meer Statues, but flout at, yea repreſent them as perſons not worthy to be ſuffered to live in the World, who cannot be ſo far bewitched out of both their Reaſon and Senſe, but ſtand up for the Common Intereſt of Mankind, and maintain the Common Liberties and Priviledges thereof, than which none is more innate, nor more approved, either among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans or Heathens (ſome few ſelf-deſigning, and other weak perſons hood-winkt by them excepted) than that of Innocent ſelf-defence is; which if it could be removed from the minds of men, what could be expected in the World but Tyranny, and all manner of Injuſtice and Oppreſſion? And though many of late are ſufficiently perſwaded of the folly (if not wickedneſs) of thoſe principles, and returned to their right wits again, yet how many are there ſtill, whom either the Vanity of being accounted conſtant in their Opinions, or ſome worſe principle, keeps as Stiff and Tenacious of their miſchievous Tenet as ever? Yea ſo far have they blinded themſelves, that they cannot, or at leaſt will not ſee what miſchiefs they have already brought upon theſe Kingdoms, that 'twas next to a Miracle that they had not been inevitably ruined; and tho' a year ago many of them were ſenſible of their being too active in propagating ſuch principles, and ſeemed to reſolve for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not to be ſo inſtrumental in their own Thraldom, yet no ſooner was the Storm over, but they ſtraight licked up their Vomit again,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98001:2"/>and have become as great Wonderers after that Beaſt as ever, and as ready to condemn all thoſe that maintain that great principle of Self-defence, which is the only Bulwark againſt Slavery and Tyranny, as Rebellious, Seditious, Enemies to Kings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Wherein they bewray their Groſs Ignorance, ſince Rebellion as ſuch muſt needs conſiſt in the Offenſive, and not in the Defenſive part, as we may ſee from both Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and profane Hiſtory, to inſtance but a few that of the 5 Kings of the Cities of the Plain who had ſerved <hi>Chedarlaomer</hi> 13 years, and ſo owned him for their Lawful Soveraign, and without any Acts of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion committed by him againſt them at that time rebelled: That of <hi>Corah,</hi> which has been ſo much inſiſted on, when there was not the leaſt injuſtice committed by <hi>Moſes</hi> againſt them, not to mention others, there being no juſt reaſon in both caſes why they ſhould have rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſeeing they enjoyed both their Priviledges and Lives. As for their branding honeſt ſpirited men as being Enemies to Kings, there is no man if he reflects impartially upon our Non-reſiſtance men, but muſt acknowledge that none have proved more miſchievous to Kings than they: Tho we have ſufficiency of Inſtances to prove the Truth of this, yet if we but look back to that unfortunate Prince the late King <hi>James,</hi> as being freſheſt in our memory, we may eaſily ſee it. For who knows not that that Prince might have ſtill been ſitting upon his Throne, and that whatever Zeal he might have had for his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet would not have run ſo great a riſque, as Illegally to introduce it, and to overturn the Conſtitution of our Government both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, had he not believed, that becauſe that Opinion had got ſuch an Aſcendant about his coming to the Crown that his Subjects would prove another <hi>Thebean</hi> Legion, nay hold out their Throats to the Knife, and unconcernedly ſuffer themſelves to be bubbled out of their Religion, Lives and Liberties? Nay were not the Patrons of this Aſinine Opinion opprobriouſly twitted by the Jeſuits here, when in their higheſt Elevation, that tho' His then Majeſty ſhould introduce Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and put all his Proteſtant Subjects to the Sword, yet they muſt not reſiſt him under the pain of damnation? Nor do I believe that any Prince under the Size of a Tyrant will look upon ſuch men as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than ſelf-ſeeking Paraſites, and equally Enemies both to him and his Subjects, whom a Good Prince will cheriſh as his Children. Nor will he fear, notwithſtanding it be the Received Opinion that in caſe a King ſhould degenerate into a Tyrant, and inſtead of maintaining his Subjects in their Rights and Priviledges, ſhould oppreſs and deſtroy them, they may juſtly defend themſelves againſt his Invading of their Rights,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98001:2"/>ſeeing he never deſigns any ſuch thing; and 'tis certain that while King confines himſelf to the Legal Exerciſe of his Office, there is not the leaſt ground to fear that any Party can be made againſt him, but there ſhall be 40 to one for them; and if he has reaſon to fear any, I humbly conceive it is our paſſive Obedience men; for as they do applaud even the worſt of Princes in their moſt Arbitrary Actions if they find them for their purpoſe, ſo as they may have ſome Aſcendant over them and ſuch as are like them (as too plainly appears in their now Juſtifying and wiſhing ſucceſs to that moſt Chriſtian Tyrant, not to mention others) ſo it is more than probable that they do not love to have a Good Prince over them, which is ſufficiently verified by their carriage towards their preſent Majeſties.</p>
            <p>But to come to the matter I deſign, ſince a late Anonymous Author has brought over ſome of his paſſive Commodities (as he ſays) from <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> a place where that precious Pearl is as meer a Drug as in any Empory in the World, which makes me think that our Author is ſo enamoured with his Strumpet (Non-reſiſtance that he has loſt his ſenſes, or it may be drowned them with drinking of King <hi>James</hi>'s Health:) In oppoſition thereto I ſhall only preſent the Reader with a ſhort Hiſtory of ſelf-defence, which ſhall not conſiſt meerly of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as that Hiſtory does, but a plain Relation of matters of Fact, from Hiſtories both Sacred and Profane, and ſhew that however that has been traduced by weak men, or men of depraved principles, yet in all Ages of the World it has been received as the Soveraign Remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Oppreſſion, by as Wiſe, Pious, Learned men as any that are or have been in the World, and in number infinitely exceeding the other, and that they never queſtioned the Lawfulneſs thereof when neceſſity forced them thereto (for otherwiſe it cannot be Self-defence) and have by a timeous, innocent uſe thereof preſerved their Lives, and freed themſelves from the Oppreſſions they groaned under; and have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured themſelves ſuch a laſting ſettlement that their Poſterity ſince happily enjoys what they thus purchaſed for them.</p>
            <p>The firſt Inſtance I ſhall begin with is that of <hi>David</hi> when King <hi>Saul</hi> ſought to take his life away, that he might ſecure the Kingdom the better to his Poſterity; I need not particularly inſiſt on that which firſt prompted <hi>Saul</hi> thereto, nor mention all the paſſages that fell out then; but however this is certain that <hi>David,</hi> if it was not upon the account of his defending his life againſt the unjuſt At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of King <hi>Saul,</hi> would not have had ſuch a Train, for otherwiſe it had been far more eaſy for him to have eſcaped privately by himſelf, or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98001:3"/>one or two with him than with 600 Men at his back; and it may likewiſe be evineed from his words to <hi>Abiathar,</hi> who fled to <hi>David,</hi> when <hi>Doeg</hi> the <hi>Ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mite</hi> by the appointment of <hi>Saul</hi> cut off all his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe, <hi>Stay with me, fear not, for he that ſeeketh my life ſeeketh thy life, but thou ſhalt be ſufe with me.</hi> Now I would fain know what Gloſs elſe Author would out upon theſe words; for if <hi>David</hi> had not thoſe men with deſign to defend himſelf againſt <hi>Saul</hi> and his Parties he ſhould ſend out to take him, what comfort could that be to <hi>Abiathar,</hi> that upon a Party of them coming againſt them he would ſurrender himſelf, and ſo he would bear <hi>Abiathar</hi> Company in Death? For tho' it be a trite Prowerb, <hi>Solamen miſeris ſocios habuiſſe malorum eſt,</hi> yet <hi>David</hi> would have been but a <hi>Jobs</hi> Comforter to him, to tell him; <hi>Well now, you are come to me, fear not, you and I will not reſiſt the Lords Anointed, but whenever he ſends a party to apprehend us,</hi> we will patiently undergo death together; ſince it had been more comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for him to have died with the reſt of his Fathers Family, and not have ſurvived their Deſtruction. But the laſt words of the Verſe, ſhould any man be ſo ſtupid as to put ſuch a Gloſs upon theſe Words, would confute them, <hi>viz. Thou ſhalt be ſafe with me,</hi> which undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly import this, <hi>I will defend thy Life as I will my own to the utmoſt:</hi> And tho' it be certain that <hi>David</hi> fled ſeveral times before <hi>Saul,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he could, yet the reaſon why he did ſo is expreſly mentioned in Scripture, <hi>viz. For fear of Saul,</hi> becauſe he had much more numerous Forces with him, and ſo could have eaſily cut off him and his Men; and beſides, he being in League with <hi>Jonathan,</hi> ſo as he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged even the Crown to be his due after his Fathers Death, he knew that if he could ward off the Blow till <hi>Sauls</hi> Death, he ſhould have no reaſon to fear, which made him to ſeek no more than only to ſhun en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countring with him: but had he been ſo ſhut up as that there had been no viſible way of eſcape without fighting him and his Forces, there is not the leaſt doubt to be made but he would have oppoſed him to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt. It is worth the while here to obſerve that <hi>Saul</hi> purſued <hi>David</hi> only upon a private ſpight, and as a private man; we do not hear of any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachment made upon the Priviledges and Liberties of the People in General, but that <hi>Saul</hi> acquitted himſelf indifferently, as to that, ſave in cutting off <hi>Abimelech</hi> and his Sons, and that upon a preſumptive Treaſon, in harbouring and aſſiſting with Arms and Victuals one whom he had declared Rebel, (<hi>quo Jure, quave Injuria</hi> is not mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial;) And we need not look back 100 years to find more arbitrary proceedings than this was. And if it was lawful for <hi>David</hi> to defend
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98001:3"/>his Life thus againſt that King and his Forces (who ſhed as many Prayers and Tears as ever any of our Non-reſiſtance men, had as good Audience and did likewiſe ſend forth many upon this account, yet would not lye down in the Myre and pray to God to ſave him by a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle) to ſave his own private life; much more is it lawful for a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to defend their Religion, Lives and Liberties againſt Princes, who go about to ſubvert the Fundamental Laws of the Kingdom. And tho' at 2 ſeveral times when <hi>David;</hi> had King <hi>Saul</hi> delivered into his Hands, he would not cut him off, or do him the leaſt hurt, yet that makes nothing for their purpoſe, for there is no doubt to be made, but that there were a great many in the Parliament Army, who would not have done the leaſt harm to the perſon of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. I ſhall conclude this with what St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſays of it, <hi>Hom</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Vol.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 105. Who introduces <hi>David</hi> ſpeaking on this wiſe, when he fled from before <hi>Saul</hi> and had <hi>Goliahs</hi> Sword with him, and put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into a Poſture of Defence; <q>It is better for me to be miſerable, and to ſuffer more hardſhip, than that <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould be condemned by God for the Murther of an Innocent perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot here but take notice of a Paſſage of Scripture that has been egregiouſly wreſted by our Non-reſiſtance Men, that which was ſpoken by the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> to <hi>Saul</hi> upon his not obeying the Command of God when he was ordered to deſtroy the <hi>Amalekites, viz.</hi> REBELLION IS AS THE SIN OF WITCH-CRAFT, which has been uſed by them as an Argument for Non reſiſtancetill it's become Thred bare; and yet any ordinary capacity may ſee the weakneſs of it, ſince the Rebellion here immediately ſpoken of was, not that of Subjects againſt a Prince (tho' none will deny that that which is real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rebellion is undoubtedly a great ſin) but that of King <hi>Saul</hi> againſt God: So that this is very far fetcht when uſed for an Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whatever thoſe Gentlemen are pleaſed to Interpret Rebellion. And I am ready to Conjecture that it may have ſome alluſion to what fell out towards the latter end of <hi>Sauls</hi> Reign, <hi>viz.</hi> His going upon Gods deſerting him to conſult with the Witch of <hi>Endor,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. And ſo his Rebellion was as his Witch-craft, the one having been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the beginning of his Reign, and the other upon the laſt day of his Reign, or thereabouts, for next day or 2 he was ſlain by the Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhines. Tho' this be but a Conjecture, yet it ſeems as little to wreſt the meaning of the Text, as their Gloſs. No leſs impertinently are thoſe words of <hi>Samuel</hi> when he was offended at that peoples mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing choice of a King, <hi>This ſhall be the manner of the King that ſhall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98001:4"/>rule over you</hi> applyed, when they would thereby evince that a King may lawfully do whatever he pleaſe: Whereas, he is only there telling them the Inconveniency of an evil King; and yet all the while he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpoke a word of Non-reſiſtance, as their Soveraign Duty; Yea moſt particulars there mentioned are ſuch as all Subjects willingly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to Kings; and for that of taking their Vineyards from them, we never read of its being put in Practice; for <hi>Ahab</hi> himſelf, who was a very wicked King, did not take away <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard, but proffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him one as good for it, as is clear from, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.2, 3. And when he refuſed it, that King went home diſpleaſed, but did not intend to proceed any further in it, tho <hi>Jezabel</hi> found out a trick to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way both his Life and it, by ſuborning perſons to ſwear Treaſon againſt him. So that this Argument bears not that force in it, which they would perſwade themſelves it has. I ſhall add a 3d Scripture to the former, which is likewiſe ſtretched beyond its native meaning, <hi>viz.</hi> that in the Pſalms, <hi>Touch not mine Anointed, do my Prophets no harm.</hi> For it is plain from the words preceding that theſe words were directed to Kings themſelves, to ſhew them, that tho' they were called the Lords Anointed, yet he in a ſpecial manner owned the Children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> his peculiar People as his Anointed, and they being then but few in Number, and the Kings deſigning to cut them off, he thereupon ſhewed them that he would maintain their cauſe againſt thoſe Kings, and if they wronged them, he would take it as done to himſelf, and redreſs it. And the words may very well be rendred thus with a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, and then they ſhew how remote their ſenſe is that apply it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to Kings, <hi>viz. Yea he reproved Kings for their ſakes, ſaying,</hi> [unto thoſe Kings, O ye Kings,] <hi>Touch</hi> [you] <hi>not mine Anointed, and do</hi> [you] <hi>my Prophets no harm.</hi> And I wonder if any Non-reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance man can ſay that this is not the Immediate and native ſenſe of the words: How far fetcht then muſt the Conſequences be which thoſe Gentlemen have made from them?</p>
            <p>A 2d Inſtance from Scripture, and which imports a greater Oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than a meer ſelf-defence, is that of the 10 Tribes of <hi>Iſraels</hi> revolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> upon his harſh return to their complaint of the Grievances of his Fathers Reign, and deſire that he would redreſs them, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 12.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For that King, rejecting the good advice of his Fathers ſage Counſellors, and following the Council of Young, Loyal, Tory, Dammee boys, would own his Authority from none but God, and for that inſignificant Mob, he did not value them, but ſaid that his little finger ſhould be heavier than his Fathers Loins; whereupon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98001:4"/>they fell away from him, and made choice of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the Son of <hi>Nebat</hi> for their King. And yet we no where hear them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for it in Scripture, as we find they were for Idolatry and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther crying ſins: So that it ſeems our Paſſive Obedience Gentlemen, have found out new Scriptures, who will have whatever they are pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to interpret Rebellion, one of the grievouſeſt ſins that can be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. And this thing was done by the Lord himſelf, as is clear from the Text; and therefore if it was a ſin, God muſt be the Author of it, which thoſe Gentlemen are very far from aſſerting. Yea when <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> had like a brave-ſpirited Prince, raiſed a great Army to reduce them again to Obedience to him their Natural Soveraign, the Lord forbid him by <hi>Shemajah</hi> the Prophet, in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.19. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, you ſhall not go up, nor fight againſt your Brethren the Children of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>return every man to his houſe; it is of me.</hi> As for that word, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.19. <hi>So</hi> Iſrael <hi>rebelled againſt the Houſe of</hi> David, it may be as well rendred as it is in the Margent, &amp; the Dutch, <hi>fell away,</hi> and <hi>Junius</hi> renders it, <hi>they made defection;</hi> and tho the word Rebellion had been uſed here, it would not have imported a ſinful Rebellion, no more than, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.7. Where <hi>Hezekiah</hi> is ſaid to have rebelled againſt the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> which was a fruit and effect of the Lords being with him, and proſpering him in all his undertakings. Now ſince by this Inſtance we ſee that the People without ſin (otherwiſe no doubt they would have been ſeverely reproved for it in the Scripture) did thus as to the 10 Tribes unking <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> becauſe he would not promiſe to redreſs their juſt Grievances, or to apply it to our Cuſtom, becauſe he would not take the Coronation Oath, whereby Princes bind themſelves not to oppreſs their Subjects, but to exerciſe as Gentle a Gevernment over them as poſſibly they can; how much more is it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for Subjects to defend themſelves againſt the unjuſt Invaſions and Oppreſſions of one who deſigns not only to overturn their Religion, and to introduce an Idolatrous Worſhip, but likewiſe expoſe all their Lives to the mercies of thoſe, who have been guilty of the horrideſt cruelties that ever were perpetrated upon Earth? And not only the People were never reproved for this, but even the Arch Rebel him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>Jeroboam</hi> was never charged with any guilt in this Action, tho' he was ſeverely checked for ſetting up the Golden Calves, from whence he had the denomination of <hi>Jeroboam, who made Iſrael to ſin,</hi> which he did meerly upon a Political account, leſt the 10 Tribes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorting yearly to the Paſſover and other Feaſts at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhould at laſt be perſwaded to forſake him, and return to the Houſe of <hi>David.</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98001:5"/>That he was never in the leaſt charged with any ſin in this, appears from the Words of <hi>Ahijah</hi> the Prophet, when <hi>Jeroboam</hi> ſent his Wife in diſguiſe to him about his Child that was ſick, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 14.7, 8, 9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A 3d is that of <hi>Eliſha's</hi> reſiſting thoſe commiſſionated by the King to kill him, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.32. Saying to the Elders who ſate with him in his Houſe, <hi>See ye how this Son of a Murtherer hath ſent to take away my head, look when the Meſſenger cometh, ſhut the door, and hold him faſt at the door; is not the ſound of his Maſters feet behind him?</hi> You ſee here that the King offered unjuſt Violence to the Innocent Prophet, and ſent a Ruffian to take away his life without juſt cauſe; and the Prophet defendeth himſelf againſt him as well as he could in ſuch cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, for he cauſeth hold him at the door, and violently preſs him, or preſs him betwixt the door and the Wall, which ſpeaketh vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Reſiſtance: The <hi>Dutch</hi> Annotations render it, <hi>Keep him by force at the door.</hi> And <hi>Joſephus</hi> is of Opinion that the King followed quickly after, leſt the Prophet ſhould have killed his Servant. By which it would ſeem that private perſons (for the Prophet was ſuch) might ſometimes lawfully defend themſelves againſt unjuſt violence offered them by Kings or their Emiſſaries: And if ſo, there cannot remain the leaſt doubt of the Lawfulneſs of a Community, or Body of the Peoples defending themſelves againſt the Unjuſt Encroachments of a King upon their Religion, Lives and Liberties, when he is endeavouring to ſubvert the fundamental Conſtitutions, on which the Preſervation of all depends.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The City of <hi>Libna,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.10. Revolted (which is the higheſt degree of reſiſtance) from wicked King <hi>Jehoram,</hi> who when he obtained the Kingdom of his Father, ſtrengthned himſelf, and ſlew all his Brethren with the Sword, and likewiſe ſeveral of the Princes of <hi>Iſrael, v.</hi> 4. and walked in the way of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as the houſe of <hi>Ahab</hi> did, for he took <hi>Ahabs</hi> Daughter to Wife, and wrought that which was evil in the ſight of the Lord, <hi>v.</hi> 6. And made him high places in the Mountains of <hi>Judah,</hi> and cauſed the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to commit fornication, and compelled <hi>Judah</hi> thereto, <hi>v.</hi> 11, 13. And becauſe he had thus forſaken the Lord God of his Fathers, the City of <hi>Libnah</hi> revolted from him: And this is the Judgment of ſeveral Learned Commentators; <hi>Cornelius à La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pide</hi> on the place ſaith, <hi>Libna</hi> made defection from the King becauſe of his wickedneſs. And <hi>Sanctius</hi> on, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.22. <hi>Libnah</hi> revolted from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under his hand, for he had forſaken the God of his Fathers. And <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Martyr, The cauſe is deſcribed in the Chronicles to have been the Kings
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98001:5"/>wickedneſs, who went about to force his Subjects to Idolatry, which even thoſe of</hi> Libnah <hi>would not ſit with, and that with good reaſon, for we muſt obey the King but to the Altars, and ſince they had the poſſeſſion of that Land on this condition, that they ſhould worſhip him there according to his Word, by right thereof they ought not to ſuffer Idolatry.</hi> And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſome ſay; <hi>This imports not the Impulſive cauſe of the Revolt, or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive which they had before their Eyes (for in the ſame verſe and period it is ſaid, the</hi> Edomites <hi>alſo revolted from him, becauſe he had forſaken the Lord God of his Fathers, and the</hi> Edomites <hi>loved not the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) but the meritorious cauſe on</hi> Jehorams <hi>part is pointed at:</hi> It may be anſwered, That the Text itſelf and Commentators, to whom we may add <hi>Jackſon,</hi> on 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8. And the <hi>Dutch</hi> Annotations on the ſame place, give this as the Impulſive cauſe and only Motive they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Eyes. 2. It is obvious to any from the very Text itſelf that this is very remote from the true ſcope thereof, for <hi>v.</hi> 8. It's ſaid, that <hi>in his days the</hi> Edomites <hi>revolted from under the Dominion of</hi> Judah, <hi>and made themſelves a King,</hi> without any mention of this as the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive cauſe thereof; and mention is made again of their revolt, <hi>v.</hi> 10. upon <hi>Jehorams</hi> endeavouring to reduce them to his Dominion; and then mention is made of <hi>Libnahs</hi> Revolt in a diſtinct ſentence with the cauſe and only Motive thereof; <hi>Becauſe he had forſaken the Lord God of his Fathers:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Azariah</hi> and the fourſcore Prieſts with him oppoſed King <hi>Uz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah,</hi> and would not ſuffer him to offer Incenſe (not conſidering it ſeems that he was the Lords Anointed) yea and when he perſiſted therein and took the Incenſe in his hand, and was ſmitten with Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy they thruſt him out of the Temple, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.17, &amp;c. <hi>They ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled him with force, ſtood againſt him,</hi> the LXX ſay, <hi>they reſiſted him,</hi> Vatablus, <hi>they thruſt him out of the Place, Arias Montanus,</hi> they cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to make haſte, <hi>Jerom.</hi> They drove him out in haſte; when he went into the Temple to burn Incenſe upon the Altar of Incenſe on ſome ſolemn day, (as <hi>Joſephus</hi> is of opinion.) So that here was a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſiſtance of him; 1. By words, a <hi>What doeſt thou O King?</hi> (to uſe that Expreſſion of the Proverbs ſo much abuſed by our Paſſive-Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence Champions) it appertaineth not unto thee, to offer In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, that Office by God is appointed to the Prieſts only; and they very peremptorily charged him to go out of the Temple; and when upon his Obſtinacy he was ſmitten with Leproſy, they not in the leaſt regarded that he was Gods Anointed, but forceably drove him out of the Temple. Had thoſe Prieſts been of our Gentlemens Opinion, they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98001:6"/>would have ſaid, God forbid that we ſhould ſtretch out our hand any ways againſt Lords Anointed, it is true that God hath forbid any to offer Incenſe but the Prieſts, but he is unaccountable for what he does, we have no power to oppoſe him, tho' in a humble way we will Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion him, and pray his Majeſty not to do that which will ſo much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God againſt him: And when he was turned Leper, how might they upon the ſame reaſon have ſaid, that tho' 'tis true that God hath ſaid that a Leper ſhall not enter into the Congregation, yet that was ſpoken of the Body of the People but not of Kings, who whatever they do muſt not be reſiſted by us, ſeeing they are accountable to none but God, and thorefore let us not thruſt him out. But we find no ſuch Loyal Language proceeding out of their Mouths to this King. And hence it will undoubtedly follow, That a Prince, when he Rages and Tyrannizes contrary to all Juſtice and reaſon may be oppoſed by his Subjects.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And which is yet more than has been Inſtanced, In 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.27. After that <hi>Amaziah</hi> turned away from following the Lord, the People made a Conſpiracy againſt him, and after that he having notice thereof, fled to <hi>Lachiſh,</hi> they ſent men who ſlew him there, and afterwards ſet up his Son <hi>Uzziah</hi> upon the Throne. Now we do not read in Scripture that ever the People were reproved for this, nor was it ever reckoned afterwards to have been one of the procuring ſins of all the Judgments that were poured out upon that Nation: And which, I think is very material, <hi>Uzziah</hi> upon his Acceſſion to the Crown never in the leaſt called any of them in Queſtion for it, as was done in other caſes, when ſome of their Servants treacherouſly roſe up againſt them and ſlew them. Theſe Inſtances I thought fit to lay before the Reader out of the Old Teſtament, that they may be laid in the Ballance with what our Non-Reſiſtance men ſay to the contrary.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only adduce one Inſtance out of the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> and 'tis this.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Hiſtory of the <hi>Macchabees</hi> is a clear Example of private perſons reſiſting and defending themſelves from the unjuſt Oppreſſion and Blood-ſhed of their then Soveraigns: for when <hi>Antiochus</hi> was compelling them to forſake God, and acting the Tyrant over-them, <hi>Matthias</hi> a Prieſt and his Sons made open Reſiſtance; and afterwards <hi>Mattathias</hi> and thoſe with him, hearing how <hi>Matthias</hi> out of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernice Superſtition would not ſight in their own defence on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-day, reſolved upon all occaſions to defend themſelves, their Lives and Laws, and to take all advantage of the Enemy; and it pleaſed God
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98001:6"/>ſo to bleſs their ſo Laudable deſigns that they recovered their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Laws and Liberties, and overthrew their Oppreſſors in ſeveral Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels. And <hi>Oſiander Enchirid Contr. c.</hi> 9. <hi>de Mag. Pol.</hi> Teſtifies that this was done by the Encouragement and Aſſiſtance of the Spirit of God. And if any ſhould alledge that this Inſtance is Impertinent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they think that <hi>Antiochus</hi> was not their Lawful Supream Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, but only a Tyrant without Title, I will recommend them to <hi>Grotius</hi> words in this caſe, who is of ſo great Authority with them in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things. In his Book <hi>de Jure Belli &amp; Pacis, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 7. he hath theſe words about it. <hi>Like unto this appeareth that deed of the</hi> Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees, <hi>for whereas ſome think to defend theſe Arms upon this ground, that</hi> Antiochus <hi>was not King, but an Invader, it ſeems fooliſh to me, ſince in all the Hiſtory of the</hi> Macchabees, <hi>and of ſuch as took their part, they never name</hi> Antiochus <hi>any thing elſe but their King; and that not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon, for long before this the Jews had acknowledged the Authority of the</hi> Macedonians, <hi>unto whoſe Power and Place</hi> Antiochus <hi>did ſucceed; and as to that that the Law forbiddeth that any Stranger ſhould be ſet over them, that is to be underſtood of a voluntary Election, and not of what the people might through neceſſity be forced to do. And, whereas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay that the</hi> Macchabees <hi>uſed only the right of the People,</hi> cui <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> deberetur, <hi>neither is that ſolid, for the Jews being at firſt overcome by</hi> Nebuchadnezzar, <hi>and ſubjected to him by the Law of War, by the ſame Law they did obey the</hi> Medes <hi>and</hi> Perſians, <hi>who ſucceeded unto the</hi> Chaldeans, <hi>and all this Empire came at length into the hands of the</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians: <hi>Hence it is that</hi> Tacitus <hi>reckoned the Jews amongſt the baſeſt of ſuch as ſerved theſe</hi> Aſſyrians, Medes <hi>and</hi> Perſians. <hi>Nor did they require any thing by Stipulation from</hi> Alexander <hi>and his Succeſſors, but without any conditions give themſelves up unto their Power, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they had been under the Command of</hi> Darius. <hi>And if at any time the Jews were permitted to uſe their own Rites and Laws, that was but a begged Right, which they had through the Indulgence of the Kings, but not through any Imperial Law. So that there is nothing that can defend the</hi> Macchabees <hi>but moſt imminent and certain danger.</hi> Thus he.</p>
            <p>Innumerable Inſtances of Self-defence might be adduced out of ancient Greek and Roman Hiſtories; but ſince they are not of ſuch force as thoſe are which are produced from People profeſſing the true Religion, I ſhall forbear it, and apply my ſelf to adduce Inſtances from the practice of People under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>'Tis true in the New Teſtament we meet but with one Inſtance
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98001:7"/>of ſelf-defence, and there it's prohibited: But not ſo forbid as if it were ſinful, much leſs ſo great a ſin as many of late have held it forth to be: For whereas in other places of the new Teſtament our Saviour rebuked <hi>Peter</hi> very ſeverely with a <hi>Get thee behind me, Satan,</hi> at this time, when he drew his Sword in his Maſters defence, he only ſaid, <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thus far, for thus it muſt be:</hi> Now had this been a ſin, it cannot be ſuppoſed but that our Saviour would not only have forbid it at this time, but have warned his Diſciples againſt it for ever; And as to the words, <hi>He that uſeth the Sword ſhall periſh by the Sword,</hi> that makes nothing at all for Non-reſiſtance, ſince if taken meerly literally it would equally prohibit all fighting whatſoever, tho' againſt a Forreign Enemy Invading us, or againſt a Robber that is about to take away our Lives, which yet none will ſay is unlawful. And tho' ſome would make our Saviours Practice in this point a Rule for us, yet there is not the leaſt ground for it; For if we conſider the great Work of Redemption which he came into the World to accompliſh, we may eaſily ſee that we are not to imitate every particular practice of his; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that tho' he would not defend himſelf againſt any, yet we may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully do it, when neceſſity requires.</p>
            <p>But ſince thoſe that plead ſo much for Non-reſiſtance lay their main ſtreſs on <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. We ſhall briefly hint at it. And it ſeems very plain that Obedience and Subjection to Lawful Magiſtrates is here inſiſted on, and not to Tyrants: For, 1. We are here commanded to be Subject to that Power which is <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi> or as it is in <hi>Peter,</hi> the <hi>Ordinance of Man:</hi> But Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny is neither, but the <hi>Ordinance of Satan. Gerhard de Magiſt. Polit. N.</hi> 54. Tells us that the Apoſtle accurately diſtinguiſhes betwixt the Power and the abuſe of the Power, and ſays that the Power, and not the abuſe of it, is from God, and likewiſe betwixt the Office it ſelf, and the Perſon in the Office, and <hi>Beza</hi> and many other Learned Men are of the ſame Opinion. 2. The Power that is not to be reſiſted is for <hi>the terror of evil doers, and encouragement of thoſe that do well:</hi> But Tyranny is an encourager of thoſe that do evil, and a perſecutor of thoſe that do well. 3. He is not to be reſiſted <hi>who is the Miniſter of God for good:</hi> But Tyrants are not the Miniſters of God, nor for good, but of <hi>Satan?</hi> And ſo the Text inforces our Subjection, not to ſuch as are <hi>Tyrants,</hi> or abuſe their Power to the Oppreſſion and Deſtruction of Subjects, but to ſuch as carry themſelves as the Miniſters of God, for the Ends appointed, <hi>viz.</hi> the Advancement of Order and Peace in the World: So that notwithſtanding any thing in this Text, Tyrants, or rather Tyranny may be oppoſed.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98001:7"/>
            <p>If any object, That there was no need St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould inſiſt ſo much on ſubmiſſion to Magiſtrates that anſwered the true ends of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſince that was a Duty ſo plain that it needed not be much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcated: I anſwer, with the abovementioned <hi>Gerhard, Polit. N.</hi> 34. and other Learned Men, That St. <hi>Paul</hi> gave this Exhortation to warn Chriſtians to beware of that Hereſy that then got up (which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience mentions himſelf) <hi>that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed all Governments,</hi> and accounted them the contrivance of evil Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and likewiſe to prevent Chriſtians from being led aſide by the Jews, who held it unlawful to yield any Subjection to the Romans; And therefore to confute theſe Errors, the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Let every Soul be Subject to the Higher Powers;</hi> and St. <hi>Peter. Be ſubject to every Ordinance of Man.</hi> But neither of theſe Apoſtles, carries this Non-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and Subjection to them, to that heighth as thoſe men have done of late. Nor does either of them to ſay, that tho' a King were going to deſtroy his Subjects, yet they muſt not defend themſelves, nor reſiſt the Lords anointed, tho' never ſo great a Tyrant; which undoubtedly they would have done had they deſigned ſuch a degree of Non-reſiſtance as was lately ſo much cryed up here.</p>
            <p>It may likewiſe be anſwered that the Apoſtles in the above-cited places are only giving Exhortations to private Chriſtians as ſuch, and not to Communities: And therefore what is ſpoken in both theſe Places does not concern the Body of a People <hi>Collectivè,</hi> but <hi>private</hi> Chriſtians in particular. And ſo it makes nothing for our Adverſaries purpoſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now proceed to give ſome farther Inſtances of Self-Defence; and ſince the Primitive Chriſtians lye in my way I ſhall a little conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, eſpecially ſince ſo much ſtreſs is laid upon their practice; but if no ſtronger Argument can be produced than their practice, it will be very weak.</p>
            <p>For, Should we make their practice our Rule in this point, we muſt do the ſame in others that are parallel: And ſo we ſhould hold it unlawful for us to defend our ſelves againſt a Rabble that have no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority at all: For <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us that they would not reſiſt the Common People that aſſailed them without any Law, and ſeems to put no difference between reſiſting Emperors and private perſons, as appears by his words; <hi>Idem ſumus Imperatoribus qui &amp; vicinis noſtris—Quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque enim non licet in Imperatorem, id nec in quenquam.</hi> We behave our ſelves after the ſame manner to Emperors as we do to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.—Whatever is not lawful to do againſt the Emperor, is not lawful againſt any Man. And ſeveral of the Fathers thought it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98001:8"/>to kill even a private man upon their own defence. See <hi>Ambroſe de Offic. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>Auguſt. Epiſt. ad Public.</hi> 154. <hi>&amp; de lib. Arbit. c.</hi> 5. But which is yet more, many of thoſe Chriſtians would not ſo much as flee from the fury of their Perſecutors; Yea <hi>Tertul.</hi> condemned flight in time of perſecution, <hi>lib. de ſuga in perſecut.</hi> Many of them run wilfully upon perſecution, when they had no call from God to do it: Nay, ſo ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious were they of Martyrdom, that the Church at laſt was forced to emit a Declaration, that if any wilfully expoſed themſelves to danger unleſs he were taken up by the Perſecutors, he ſhould not be reputed a Martyr. So that as the practice of the Primitive Chriſtians in theſe abovementioned is (as all acknowledge) no Preſident for us, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be in the other, ſince it is certain that what they did was rather the Effect of a deſire of Martyrdom, which, as <hi>Sulpitius Severus</hi> ſays they gaped more after than men in his days did after Biſhopricks, than a firm perſwaſion of the neceſſity of Non-reſiſtance in all caſes. For we never read that they maintained it unlawful for People to defend themſelves in any caſe. And Beſides, They had no Law on their ſide; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their caſe was vaſtly different from ours, who have our Religion and Liberties confirmed to us by ſo many Acts of Parliament.</p>
            <p>But even then we find ſome Inſtances of ſelf defence; for about the Year 235, ſome men inhabiting <hi>Mareota,</hi> with force reſcued <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> out of the hands of thoſe that were carrying him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; ſee <hi>Blondel Schol, in Grot. de Imp. Sum. Pot.</hi> And the ſame <hi>Blon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> tells us that about the year 310 the <hi>Armenians</hi> defended themſelves againſt <hi>Maximius,</hi> who came againſt them with an Army becauſe of their Religion.</p>
            <p>And ſince the World was bleſt with Chriſtian Emperors, and had Laws made on their ſide, we find Chriſtians behaved themſelves other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than they did under Heathen Emperors, eſpecially when they were under ſuch Princes as Apoſtatized from the true Religion, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly <hi>Julian the Apoſtate:</hi> For the Chriſtians of thoſe times did not only upbraid him, and prayed for his Deſtruction, but plainly ſhewed, that if he had uſed forcible means againſt them, they would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted him, as plainly appears from <hi>Gregory Nazianzen, Orat.</hi> 19. <hi>p.</hi> 307. and in his firſt Oration againſt <hi>Jultan.</hi> And that Tyrant was ſenſible enough of that, and therefore he never uſed open force againſt them, but took what underhand Methods he could to ſupplant them, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from the Words of the ſaid Father, <hi>Nos enim ſi vis inferatur, acriores, obſtantioreſque futuros, ac Tyrannidi obnixum pietatis tuendae ſtudium objecturos,</hi> &amp;c, <hi>i. e.</hi> If he had uſed violence, he knew that we
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98001:8"/>would be more Active and Refractory, and would have oppoſed to his Tyranny a firm Reſolution to defend our Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I might adduce many other Authors of undoubted Credit to confirm this; but more have been ſhewed already than the Champions of Non-reſiſtance ſhall ever be able to anſwer, and therefore for brevities ſake I omit them, and ſhall bring ſome Inſtances of the Primitive Chriſtians de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending both their Paſtors and themſelves againſt their Perſecutors.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When the Emperor at <hi>Macedonius</hi> Inſtigation, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a Proclamation that the Churches of ſuch as em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the Creed,<note place="margin">Socrat. Hiſt. Eccl. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> containing the clauſe of one Subſtance ſhould be thrown down, and the Commiſſioners for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing Churches went to put it in Execution, a great number of Novatians and others that maintained the Doctrine of one Subſtance, pulled down that Church, removed it to another place, and there e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected it again — Again <hi>Macedonius</hi> underſtanding that there were many both at <hi>Paphlagonia</hi> and <hi>Mantinium;</hi> that could not be commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly removed by Eccleſiaſtical Authority, perſwaded the Emperor to ſend 4 Bands of Souldiers into <hi>Paphlagonia,</hi> to terrify the Inhabitants, and make them turn <hi>Arians.</hi> But the Inhabitants of <hi>Mantinium,</hi> kindled with a fervent Zeal for the Orthodox Religion, went againſt the Souldiers with cheerful minds and valiant Courage; after they had muſtered a great Body, and provided themſelves with the beſt Arms they could procure, they marched to meet their Enemies, and fought them; in this Battel many of the <hi>Paphlagonians</hi> fell, but few, if any, of the Souldiers eſcaped. He likewiſe tells us in the ſame place, that when this <hi>Macedonius</hi> was about to deſtroy the Temple in which <hi>Conſtantine</hi> lay interred, and deſigned to tranſlate the Emperors Bones, the People reſiſted him, and when he got the Bones carried into the Church where <hi>Acacius</hi> the Martyr was buried, the Multitude of the contrary ſide ran thither in haſte; and this occaſioned a very great Slaughter, and the Porch unto the Street run with Blood, and was full of Dead Bodies. And the Emperor was mightily enraged at <hi>Macedonius</hi> for his precipitancy in this Action.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Chriſtians in <hi>Perſia,</hi> when they were op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by <hi>Barabanes</hi> or <hi>Baratanes</hi> King thereof,<note place="margin">Hiſt. Tripartit. l. <hi>11.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> fled to the Romans, to beg their help; upon which and ſome other cauſes the Romans declared War againſt that King. It is true they did not riſe up againſt that King when they remained in his Countrey, becauſe they were not in a caſe to do it. But <hi>Socrates, lib.</hi> 7. declares that they came as Suppliants to the Romans, and craved that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98001:9"/>they would commiſerate their caſe, and not ſuffer them to be ſo oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: And the Emperor made this a great cauſe of the War: And when the <hi>Perſian</hi> King demanded back his Fugitives (as our Non-reſiſtance Gentlemen's moſt dearly beloved Champion did a few years ago) they anſwered they would not do it; and that they would not only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſet the Suppliants at Freedom, and deliver them from their Oppreſſors; but alſo that they would undergo any thing for the good of the Chriſtian Religion, and (as <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaith, <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 18.) they deſigned not only to aid them, but alſo by all means endeavour to maintain the Quarrel of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was forced to flee out of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> and <hi>Gregorius</hi> was brought thither with armed Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,<note place="margin">Socrat. Hiſt. Eccleſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> o. <hi>8. Greek Copy, 11.</hi>
               </note> and put in poſſeſſion of the Church, the Citizens of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> notwithſtanding that <hi>Syrianus</hi> the Captain under the Emperor was there with 5000 Armed Men, were ſo diſpleaſed at what was done, that they ſet St <hi>Denis</hi> Church on fire.</p>
            <p n="4">4. After the Orthodox at Conſtantinople had choſen <hi>Paul</hi> for their Biſhop on the Death of <hi>Euſebius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem l. <hi>2.</hi> o. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> the Emperor ſent <hi>Hermogenes</hi> the Captain to thruſt <hi>Paul</hi> out of the Church, and when he came to execute his Commiſſion by force, the People prepared themſelves to aid their Biſhop, broke into the Houſe where <hi>Hermogenes</hi> was, pulled him out and killed him. And when <hi>Paul</hi> was again placed in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the Emperor ſent <hi>Philip</hi> the Preſident to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him, and to ſet up <hi>Macedonius</hi> the <hi>Arian</hi> in his ſtead. But <hi>Philip</hi> was ſo afraid of the People (it ſeems the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance was not much preached up among them, otherwiſe he would not have been afraid, for they were very obſervant of their Teachers Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) that he went ſtraight into the publick Bath called <hi>Zenxippus,</hi> and ſent for <hi>Paul;</hi> and being in fear of the Multitude, that flocked thither upon Suſpicion, conveyed him ſecretly out at a Window: Then he and <hi>Macedonius</hi> went into the Church, and were guarded all along with Souldiers, and when they came to the door, there was ſo great a crowd that they could not enter, till ſome thouſands, were killed. And likewiſe <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperor durſt not, for fear of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">Socr. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> put to death thoſe 80 Prieſts that came to ſupplicate in name of all the reſt in <hi>Nicomedia</hi> and were Commanded to be killed.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Several Monks inhabiting Mount <hi>Nitria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> eſpouſed <hi>Cyrills</hi> Quarrel, and coming to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> aſſaulted the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98001:9"/>Lieutenant in his Chariot, with Stones, ſo that his Guard was forced to betake themſelves to flight.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When the Emperor had baniſhed <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the year 404.<note place="margin">Hiſt. Tripartit. l. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> The People flocked together about the Palace, ſo that the Emperor, to pacify them, was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to recal him from his Baniſhment.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was baniſhed by <hi>Valentinian,</hi> at the Inſtigation of his Mother <hi>Juſtina,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> the People did reſiſt ſuch as came to carry him away; ſuch was their Zeal for the Truth, and Love to their injured Biſhop, and choſe rather to loſe their Lives, than ſuffer their Paſtor to be taken away by the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,<note place="margin">Ruffin Hiſt. l. <hi>11.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> that were ſent to drag him out of the Church.</p>
            <p>More Inſtances might be adduced from thoſe times, which ſhews of how little account the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance was in thoſe days: And that they were far from thinking it a damnable Doctrine, that People might lawfully defend themſelves againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions of Tyrannous Princes upon their Rights and Priviledges. I ſhall now deſcend to ſhew what Inſtances of Self-defence are extant ſince the time that Popery prevailed in the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>The firſt Inſtance we have after the Prevalency of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery over true Chriſtianity is that of the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> or <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingenſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thuan. Preaf. in hiſt. ſui temp. &amp; lib. <hi>5.</hi> A. <hi>1550.</hi>
               </note> (who are undoubtedly the Ancienteſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in <hi>Europe</hi>) who had been a long time oppreſſed by Princes that had given up their Power to the Beaſt, and endeavoured by all means to ſuppreſs the true Religion there, and uſed now and then to take off ſome of the Profeſſors thereof, putting many of them to exquiſite Torments: But their Enemies, being but Novices in reſpect of thoſe who followed them, and not having then found out that Sovereign Method of extirpating Hereticks by Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cring, had their Addreſs to open force, and made greater Preparations againſt them than ever were formerly made againſt the Turks, that they might make an end of them all at once: Which thoſe Innocent People perceiving, they got together upon their own defence, and had ſeveral Battels with them; and tho' it pleaſed God to let their Enemies have the Victory, and the poor people were forced to fly; yet their flight contributed much to the Advancoment of the Goſpel, for being thus ſcattered, they ſowed the ſeed of the Goſpel through ſeveral Places of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Proteſtants of <hi>Bohemia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theat. Mat. p. <hi>681.</hi> Mut. in Chron. l. <hi>27.</hi> p. <hi>314, 315.</hi>
               </note> after they ſaw that <hi>John Huſs</hi> and <hi>Jerom</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98001:10"/>by their Enemies, (the former of whom was moſt unjuſtly taken off by his adverſaries, when he had the publick faith of the Emperor <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> for his ſafe appearance) thought it time to look to their Preſervation, when they ſaw that they were all deſigned for ſlaughter; and therefore they ſtood up to defend themſelves and their Religion; their firſt Leader was <hi>Ziska</hi> (or <hi>Joannes de Trots Nova</hi>) who behaved himſelf ſo valiantly that the <hi>Germans</hi> were not able to ſtand before him; and when he was a dying he ordered a Drum to be made of his Skin, affirming that whenever his Enemies heard the ſound thereof, they would forthwith betake themſelves to flight. This War con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued 13 years, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neas Sylvius</hi> ſpeaking of it ſaith, <hi>that it would be more admired than believed by Poſterity.</hi> The Emperor ſent 3 Armies againſt them. <hi>viz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> one under the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> another under the Marqueſs of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> and a 3d under the Biſhop of <hi>Trier,</hi> who in all conſiſted of 200000 Men. Yet they were routed in ſeveral Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, and forced to go out of <hi>Bohemia.</hi> Several Cardinals were with them, to curſe thoſe Rebels of damnable Commonwealth Principles with Bell. Book and Candle, with all <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency</hi> that could be, and yet notwithſtanding, that Loyal Army could not ſtand before this factious Rabble, tho' a Cardinal gave them his Bleſſing, told them that they fought againſt Hereticks, Dogs, and what not? promiſed them Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, Apoſtolical Bleſſings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet all would not do. For as good a cauſe as thoſe Men had, <hi>viz.</hi> fighting for their Gracious Soveraign, they were forced to betake themſelves to that which was the others part to have done, <hi>viz.</hi> Prayers and Tears, and run for it. And had thoſe people continued unanimous, they might without Interruption have enjoyed the freedom of their Religion and other Priviledges till this day, but they being made up of 2 ſorts, as generally all Churches are, the one, and by far the greateſt, ſtood up only for the Cup in the Sacrament, who were therefore called <hi>Calixtines,</hi> in other points agreeing with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The other called <hi>Taborites</hi> far inferiour in Number, rejected likewiſe the Doctrine and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as ſuperſtitious and falſe; the other Party, by the perſwaſion of <hi>Rokyzana</hi> who gaped after the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Prague,</hi> were reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> retaining only the uſe of the Cup; and when the <hi>Taborites</hi> proteſted againſt them for it; this Party to ſhew that they were in earneſt reconciled to that Church, and had received the Gifts of that Spirit that are diffuſed there, <hi>viz.</hi> Blind-zeal, Blood thirſtineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> raiſed forces againſt them and gave them a total Overthrow, <hi>Anno</hi> 1434. So that they dragooned them
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98001:10"/>to Non-reſiſtance; for ſince they had now no force againſt them, they were forced to reſtrict themſelves to what defence they could make by the Sword of the Word and Patience. The City <hi>Tabor</hi> which they had built was likewiſe Sackt, and they diſperſed. But <hi>Rokyzana,</hi> when he ſaw the Pope tantalized him with the vain hopes of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhoprick, began to thunder out afreſh againſt the Pope as Antichriſt, and to ſeparate from the Latin, and unite with the Greek Church. But the Pope, knowing that the only way to ſtop a Dogs Mouth, when he is a ſnarling, is to throw him a Bone, gave him his Biſhoprick; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which this good Biſhop was pleaſed to interceed with King <hi>George</hi> to grant them free Liberty to dwell in the Mountainous parts of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſia;</hi> whither they went in the year 1459. Giving themſelves wholly to the reading of the Scriptures and Prayer; their Faith and Lives being framed according to Apoſtolical ſimplicity. But their Peace was not long lived, as it ſeldom ever was in a Church, when it had no other means left it but Prayers and Tears; for that good Biſhop (it's like out of a pious deſign to nip ſo dangerous a faction as that was in the bud, and to advance Mother Churches peace) informing the King what dangerous men thoſe were, perſwaded him to uſe his fatherly Chaſtiſement to reduce his Rebellious Subjects to their due Obedience, which could not be done, without an <hi>Uniformity</hi> in matters of Religion and Ceremonies; So that they were forced to betake themſelves to the Woods and Caves, where they durſt not kindle fire in the day time, in the extremity of Cold, leſt the ſmoke ſhould diſcover them to their Enemies. See <hi>Regenſvolc. Hiſt. Slavon. p.</hi> 2.29, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates a great many things of theſe Brethren even till the times of <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> who himſelf did not diſapprove their Opinion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When in the year 1529 a Meeting of the States of the Empire was held <hi>at Spire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sleidan, l. vi, vii. xvii. Thuan l. iv. Hiſt.</note> a Decree was publiſhed which very much ſtraitned the Liberty of the Proteſtants, <hi>Joh.</hi> Elector of <hi>Saxony, Geo.</hi> of <hi>Brandenburgh, Erneſt</hi> and <hi>Fran.</hi> of <hi>Lunenburgh Phil.</hi> of <hi>Haſſia,</hi> proteſted publickly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it on <hi>April</hi> 19. And ſeveral Cities, as <hi>Strasburg, Norimberg, Ulme</hi> and others ſubſcribed their Proteſtation; from which time they had the name of Proteſtants. And when they were threatned a War by the Emperor, the reſt of the States of the Empire and all the Popiſh Faction, they entred into a League at <hi>Smalcald,</hi> on <hi>Nov.</hi> 23. to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Religion and Liberties, againſt their unjuſt Invaſions. And afterwards in the Year 1547. The Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> and the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave of <hi>Haſſia</hi> gave the Emperor battel at <hi>Mulberg</hi> where they were
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98001:11"/>routed by his Army, and <hi>Friderick</hi> Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> after he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſeveral wounds was taken Priſoner. And in the year 1552 <hi>Mais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice of Saxony</hi> made War upon the Emperor, to procure the Landgrave of <hi>Haſſia</hi> his Father in Law his Liberty. And he made ſo great Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he was upon the Emperor before he was aware, and did ſo ſurprize him, that he made him fly from <hi>Mulhouſia</hi> in the Middle of the Night, and ſet at Liberty both the Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> and the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave. And when <hi>Maurice</hi> had almoſt over-run all <hi>Germany,</hi> a Peace was concluded at <hi>Paſſaw,</hi> by the Mediation of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> wherein Liberty of Religion according to the <hi>Auſpurg</hi> Confeſſion was eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is no leſs certain, that the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants defended themſelves againſt Authority,<note place="margin">Thuan. Sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id. Contin. Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſius, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> when they ſaw that they were deſigned as ſheep for the Slaughter and that great Armies were raiſed there, and much blood ſhed, ſo that Rivers are ſaid to be coloured with Blood. And when it pleaſed God ſo to defend thoſe diſtreſſed Proteſtants that their Bloody Enemies, could not obtain their ends by open Hoſtility, they betook themſelves to that Inhumane way of Maſſacring, and having gathered together moſt of the leading Proteſtants of <hi>France</hi> under pretence of ſolemnizing the Marriage of that Kings Daughter with the King of <hi>Navar,</hi> they cut them off in one night, to the number of 70000, that ſo the Countrey People being deſtitute of their Leaders might be a Prey to them. Now had our ſo much magnified Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance been in force there, there had been no need of having recourſe to ſuch Inhumane a Method as this; for there needed no more, if ſo be they would have made no Oppoſition in their own defence, but ſtringed them up in hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds and thouſands.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is likewiſe ſufficiently known how the Proteſtants of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> defended themſelves againſt the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical Oppreſſions and Cruelties of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> and the Duke <hi>de Alva</hi> his Governour,<note place="margin">Stad. de Bello Belg. Grot. Mete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran, Redan.</note> when the Inquiſition was ſet up there, whereby ſeveral of their Nobles were cut off, and that at that time <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> made his Eſcape to his Father in Law <hi>Maurice</hi> Elector of <hi>Saxony:</hi> At the news of whoſe eſcape, <hi>Granvellan</hi> ſaid, <hi>that it ſignified, little that the Counts of</hi> Horn <hi>and</hi> Egmond <hi>were taken, ſince that Quiet thinking</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam <hi>had made his Eſcape.</hi> He returned afterwards, and was made uſe of by God as the Great Inſtrument of the Delivery of Gods Church and People there, and defended them againſt their Bloody Enemies:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98001:11"/>And had not God ſtirred up this great Prince to put a ſtop to that Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants fury, and to reſiſt his unjuſt Incroachments upon the Peoples Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and defend the true Apoſtolick Faith againſt the Romiſh Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, 'tis a great Queſtion whether that had not ſtill been a Land of graven Images: And had Non-reſiſtance been in Vogue there, we had been deprived of that Great Mercy we now enjoy in having a Prince deſcended of his Loyns to reign over us: For that Noble Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had then been undoubtedly deſtroyed.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To name no more (tho' ſeveral others might be inſtanced) It is likewiſe known, how in the beginning of the Reformation in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the ſame Method was taken there, <hi>viz.</hi> that ſome of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and People when they ſaw that Queen wholly abandoned to the Counſel of her Prieſts, and when no Petitions could avail any thing, entred into a mutual League to defend themſelves againſt what unjuſt force ſhould be attempted againſt them, tho' in the mean while they treated that Queen very honourably, and would have given her all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference poſſible, but only they found it as much for her good as theirs, to prevent her embruing her hands in the Blood of the Saints, and her making oppoſition to God in that great work he was bringing about there. And it pleaſed God ſo to eſpouſe their Quarrel that they freed themſelves from that Romiſh Yoke under which they had ſo long groaned, and revived the pure Apoſtolick Religion there. By all which Inſtances it appears that the Doctrine of Self-Defence is not ſuch a Bugbear as our Non-reſiſtance men would make it: But that it has been more or leſs practiced in all Ages; nor can they ſhew half ſo many Preſidents for their Paſſive Obedience; Nor was it ever ſo injoyned in Scripture, as they maintain it: Nay I am ſure it has been more inſiſted upon here in one Sunday than ever it was in all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and Primitive Chriſtians, and others ſubſequent till of late years, and that at a time when Charters and Priviledges were taken away, traps laid againſt the Lives of ſeveral Innocent perſons and a Prince devouted to the Romiſh Intereſts ready to mount the Throne; <hi>Pio nonne conamine?</hi> Methinks were there the leaſt grain of Modeſty in thoſe perſons they ſhould be aſhamed of former actings, and not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to do them over again. But 'tis eaſily known what theſe men drive at.</p>
            <p>Nor will this ſeem harſh Doctrine to good Princes, that love their Subjects, and whoſe aim it is to anſwer that great end for which they were ſet up, no more than a Husband or Parent would be offended, if told, that if he in a mad or drunken ſit ſhould go about to Murther
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98001:12"/>his Wife, Children or Servants, they would bind him till ſuch time as his drunken fit or madneſs were over: In ſuch a caſe undoubtedly the Parent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> would be ſo far from reſenting the affront offered to his Deſpotick or Paternal Authority, that he would thank them for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; the Application is eaſie.</p>
            <p>But ſince <hi>contraria juxta ſe poſita clariùs eluceſcunt,</hi> I ſhall only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Reader with one inſtance of the reſiſting of Authority that is condemned in the Scriptures, and 'tis that of <hi>Storch</hi> and <hi>Muntzer,</hi> and the other Anabaptiſts in <hi>Germany, An.</hi> 1525. who would not give due Obedience to Magiſtrates, and under a pretext of Chriſtian Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty committed many Riots, ſo that in one Summer about 50000 of the Factious were cut off. <hi>Muntzer</hi> was the Inſtigator of this Fury, who pretended to Enthuſiaſms, Dreams, Internal Revelations, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Phanatical Whimſies. He rejected Infant-Baptiſm, ſaid that not the Scripture, but that which was ſecretly revealed to Men, was the Word of God; that God was about to ſet up a new Government, in which he would deſtroy all Earthly Potentates, and put the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into the hands of the Godly. His principal Tenet, on which all the Sedition depended was, <hi>That Wicked Magiſtrates ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and Godly Magiſtrates ſhould be ſet up in their places.</hi> By which means he gathered together a great many ſilly people, ſeized on ſeveral Cities, and committed great Outrages, till his Enthuſiaſtick Army was routed, and he himſelf taken, and puniſhed according to his deſerts.</p>
            <p>I ſay this Inſtance is quite different from thoſe we mentioned above, who never had any deſign againſt the Magiſtrates, but only endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to defend their Lives and Religion againſt the Illegal Invaſions of Tyrannous Princes; whereas theſe now mentioned had no leſs deſign than wholly to overturn that Sacred Order, they being much of the ſame Principles with Fifth Monarchy men, and thoſe of that Kidney here, by whoſe means undoubtedly, they having made ſo ſtrong a Party in the Army, King <hi>Charles</hi> I. was ſo horridly Murdered, to the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of all good Men, even ſuch as were of Opinion that Subjects might lawfully defend themſelves againſt the Encroachments of Princes upon their Laws and Liberties. And ſince our Non-reſiſtance men have taken occaſion to expoſe thoſe in our Neighbouring Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> as men of the ſame Principles, I ſhall briefly ſhew how mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly they aſperſed them; for the firſt riſing there <hi>An.</hi> 1666, was occaſioned by the Outrage of Souldiers, who grievouſly haraſſed that poor People in the Weſt of <hi>Scotland</hi> to the beggaring of many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of Families who lived in good repute there; all that while they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98001:12"/>never offered to riſe, till the barbarous Souldiers offered violence to ſome of thoſe poor diſtreſſed People, whereupon they defending them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt their Outrage, and ſeveral of the Countrey people com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in to their Aſſiſtance, they killed ſome of the Souldiers; and then expecting nothing but to be made a Sacrifice, they reſolved to defend themſelves to the utmoſt, and got together ſome 3000 Men; and tho' they took Major <hi>Turner</hi> (who had been ſo great an Oppreſſor) Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, yet they did not offer him the leaſt Injury, but ſhewed him all the Civility imaginable, as he himſelf afterward declared, which ſhews that they were not ſuch Blood-thirſty Men as they were repreſented to be: Nor did they then declare againſt the King, but only againſt the Tyranny of their Biſhops, they having no other way left of making his Majeſty ſenſible of the grievous Oppreſſions they groaned under. And that alſo in 1679 was occaſioned by the late <hi>Dundee</hi> then <hi>Claver-houſe</hi> his going againſt them, when at a Field meeting; and diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, they ſent out what armed Men they had to treat with him, who pray'd him to let them conclude their Devotions, and they would all diſperſe themſelves peaceably; but he thirſting after their Blood, and deſigning to make as many of them Priſoners as he could, (which was but little better than death, conſidering in what Jails they were Impriſoned, and how long kept) ordered his Men to Fire upon them, whereupon after receiving his Fire they diſcharged upon him, and gave him and his Men ſuch warm Entertainment that they were glad to ſcamper. This raiſing the Countrey again in a few days they were 7 or 8000 ſtrong, (a ſufficient inſtance to confute that which is with ſo much confidence whiſpered about here, that the Major part of <hi>Scotland</hi> is for Epiſcopal Government, when all <hi>Dundee</hi> and his Party could muſter up in a quarter of a years time never equalled this number) and would have increaſed to above 20000 in a few days, had not ſome of their Number been diſpatched Meſſengers thro' the Countries to pray the People not to come in, upon a difference that aroſe among them, about their Obligation to King <hi>Charles</hi> II. at penning of their Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration why they were thus in Arms; the by far greateſt number of them declaring that they did not in the leaſt deſign any thing againſt His Perſon or Authority, but would maintain the ſame according as they were obliged by their Covenant, but only they had no other way of informing his Majeſty of the ſadneſs of their condition, ſince he was encompaſſed with their Enemies; tho' ſome others, and eſpecially thoſe who had taken upon them to command the reſt, would have declared againſt him likewiſe, who no doubt might be ſeduced by ſome Romiſh
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98001:13"/>Emiſſaries, that in ſuch a juncture might eaſily inſinuate themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. By which it may appear that however thoſe Men have been maligned by black Mouths, yet they are as great Lovers of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, as Loyal, and as ready and cheerful to give a <hi>Rational</hi> and <hi>Conſciencious</hi> Obedience to Monarchs as any, tho' I confeſs I cannot boaſt of their Loyalty to the Mitre, eſpecially they cannot endure that it ſhould be ſet a top of the Crown: But how much they are for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy may be ſeen by their being ſo active in bringing home King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, tho' I will not Swear that the Proverb is not fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>re quod fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ingrato.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus deduc'd the Hiſtory of Self-Defence from the very firſt King of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and ſhewed by Inſtances, that as it began with Kings there, ſo it continued as long as the Jewiſh Government laſted, and adduced ſeveral inſtances of it in the Primitive Times, but more eſpecially in the time of the Reformation, I ſhall conclude with a few Remarks upon the Authors Preface, where he is principally concerned, he having done nothing in the reſt, but brought in ſome far fetcht Conſequences. He begins his Preface with telling you that <hi>he always thought that the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance had been a Doctrine founded in the Holy Scriptures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 1.</note> &amp;c. Which is much the ſame with the Dying Teſtimony of a late Reverend Prelate of the Church of <hi>England, who had ſucked it in with his Mothers, Milk:</hi> So that by his own words, he ſeems never to have impartially weighed the ſtrength of Argumentsion both ſides, but has taken it upon truſt, ſo that it can have little weight with any conſidering Man. But what he ſays as to its being maintained in the firſt Ages of the Reformation, is eaſilier ſaid than proved. That the firſt Reformers of the Church of <hi>England</hi> acknowledged all due ſubjection to Authority (in the ſame ſome as all other Churches, and every honeſt Man does, <hi>viz.</hi> to Princes acting Legally, and thoſe who are true Fathers of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey is beyond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l doubt. But that the firſt Reformers of the Church of <hi>England</hi> did maintain. Non-reſiſtance to the ſame heighth that this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and his Party does, is more than he can evince, ſince there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it in the 39 Articles; and the Citations which he brings out of the Homilies ſeem to affect private Perſons, and not a Community. But if this was always the profeſſed Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that it was in no caſe Lawful for Subjects to reſiſt of defend themſelves againſt the Tyrannical Invaſions of their Princes, how came ſhe to approve of and contribute to the aſſiſting of Proteſtants actually in Arms againſt their Kings, particularly thoſe of the Seven Provinces,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98001:13"/>thoſe of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and of later days the Proteſtants of <hi>Rochel?</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Author will ſcarce venture to ſay, that ſhe did not approve it: And therefore it muſt either be granted that ſhe did not maintain Non-reſiſtance in that heighth as our Author and his Party do, or that ſhe acted very diſſonantly to her Principles; which would be a great Reflection on ſo great and pious Divines as lived then: For had ſhe been of Opinion that it was unlawful for Subjects upon any account to defend themſelves againſt the unjuſt Oppreſſions of their Soveraigns, ſhe muſt needs at the ſame time ſee that it was unlawful for her to be Aider and Abettor with them, and partake of their ſin: And ſo inſtead of approving or ſending of ſupplies to them, ſhe ſhould have ſent them over that Chriſtian Exhortation, that it was their indiſpenſable Duty to ſubmit their Neeks to whatever their Soveraigns ſhould impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and ſuffer it patiently, and by no means to reſiſt their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior Powers: But we have nothing upon Record that any of her Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines at that time living objected any thing againſt it: And therefore we may with all the reaſon of the World conclude that had it been her, own caſe, ſhe would have taken the ſame Methods of defending her ſelf as other Proteſtants did. For ſhe had but a little before been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame Trials her ſelf, and therefore ſhe knew experience, than our Author, and his Party, to whom we may truely apply that of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to his Diſciples, which they have ſo often applyed to others. That <hi>they know not what manner of Spirit they are of.</hi> As to what he ſays af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ward of her Loyalty during Queen <hi>Maries,</hi> Reign: It may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that in King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth Days ſhe was but in her Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and 'tis probable that the Proteſtants at that time were not ſo, ſtrong in <hi>England,</hi> but that the Papiſts clothed with Authority would have been too hard for them: Beſides that the Proteſtant Party was at that time weakned by the Factions and Animoſities of ſome, great Men, which no doubt (as it was promoted by the Papal Faction ſo) gave great advantage to their Enemies: As by the heats of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Non-reſiſtance Men great advantage is now given to the common Enemy, ſo as they are become, very inſolent, who otherwiſe were there no Fowds amongſt us, durſt not ſo much as mutter. As to her being ſo active in bringing Queen <hi>Mary</hi> to the Throne, I think it, may deſerve enquiry, whether ſhe might not have done as well if ſhe had excluded Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and ſet up Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> immediately, upon King <hi>Edward,</hi> VI. Death: Since ſhe could have ſufficiently juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied her ſelf in ſo doing, in as much as, King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. Marriage
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98001:14"/>with her Mother was declared unlawful by the moſt Earned Divines and Caſuiſts in <hi>Europe,</hi> as being not only forbidden in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but likewiſe in the New by <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, when he told <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> that it was not lawful for him to have his Brothers Wife, which being true, Queen <hi>Mary</hi> had no Right to ſucceed, ſince ſhe was Illegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, more than the late Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> had; ſo that the Loyalty during the <hi>Marian</hi> Perſecution will not be very much to his purpoſe: And whereas that Author ſeems to obviate an Objection, <hi>viz.</hi> That Adverſaries pretend <hi>that there is ſomething of ſelf</hi> in the caſe that makes them ſtand up ſo much for Non-reſiſtance:<note place="margin">Page 1.</note> I do not ſee, nothwithſtanding all he has ſaid for the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his Party, but it is ſtill unanſwered, ſince there hath never been a time ſince the Church of <hi>England</hi> was in her moſt flouriſhing ſtate, that ſhe had occaſion to diſcover her Loyalty towards perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Princes. And ſince I know this Gentleman reckons only thoſe of his own ſize the True Churchmen (they having ſufficiently diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this to the World, when they branded the moſt Learned, moſt Religious, moſt Moderate, and numerous Party of the Church with the opprobrious Name of <hi>Timmer</hi>) I would deſire him to pauſe a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and conſider upon what ground it is that they found their Non-reſiſtance upon: There are two great commands upon which the whole Duty of Man hangs; <hi>viz. Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Thou ſhalt love by Neighbour at thy ſelf.</hi> They cannot ſay it depends on the former, at leaſt immediately; tho' there are not wanting: Inſtances of too many of that ſort of Men, who both by their Doctrine and Practice ſhewed much more Zeal to the Earthly God than to the Heavenly, as could be made appear both from their ſo much inſiſting upon their Non-reſiſtance (at a time when it might not have been thought ſo ſeaſonable) and thereby ſhuffling out thoſe Exhortations which immediately concerned the Salvation of Souls, and by the Immoral practices of ſeveral of them. We know there is a Church where more honour is ſhewed to Chriſts Vicar than to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; I wiſh it be not ſo with many of our Non-reſiſtance Men to his Vicegerent. But ſince it muſt needs be granted that it depends on the latter, the ſincerity of thoſe men in this particular may be tryed by their obſervance of other parallel Duties injoined in that ſame Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Precept, and if they be ſound tardy in thoſe we have the more reaſon to ſuſpect them in this. I have ſeveral times wondred why of all men in the World moſt of our Non-reſiſtance Champions ſhould have the confidence to pretend to the Obſervation of ſo ſelf-denying a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98001:14"/>as that ſeems to be, ſince none are readier to reſent the leaſt Injuries than they are, yea, when they will look upon that to be an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury which is really none; and if ſo be they cannot put up the leaſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed injury in the ſmalleſt things, and from which they can receive the leaſt prejudice, how can it be ſuppoſed they would do it, if it ſhould come to the loſs of Lives and Liberties? None that I know of, except the Romaniſts, have ſo far vented their Spleen, and uſed ſuch rigour and ſeverity againſt thoſe that differ from them, none have defamed and miſrepreſented them more than thoſe men who eſpecially plead for Non-reſiſtance; and how that great Chriſtian principle of Love which they ſo much pretend to, is exerciſed therein, I cannot conceive. Now if there be ſuch a failure in that ſo Obvious and Neceſſary a Duty, I think, that without any great breach of Charity a man may conclude that their Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance is no other than the Doctrine of the Bow-ſtring. For if their Loyalty, which they ſo much pretend to proceeded from an unfeigned reſpect to the Command of God, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the ſame Command would likewiſe inſpire them with Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Love and Charity towards all men, tho' never ſo much diſſenting from them, much more towards thoſe who differ only from them in ſmaller Matters. So that while they thus boaſt that they have fulfilled the Commandment of the Lord in deſtroying thoſe <hi>Amalekites,</hi> I mean thoſe ſinful Paſſions that are ſo prejudicial to Societies as well as particular Men, the bleatings of the Sheep teſtify againſt them that they are not ſuch as they would make the World believe, notwithſtanding all their ſpecious pretences to Loyalty. And ſince they uſed to inveigh ſo much againſt other perſons when they expreſt their diſlike againſt ſome Arbitrary Proceedings in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. as thoſe that <hi>ſpoke evil of Dignities,</hi> and ſo reckoned them as the worſt of men, when thoſe that but eſpouſed their darling Non-reſiſtance, tho' otherwiſe the ſtain of Humanity itſelf, much more of Chriſtianity, were good honeſt men; I only would deſire them to reflect upon their Invectives againſt the late King <hi>James,</hi> for near the laſt 2 years of his Reign, and how kindly they entertained the ſevereſt Lampoons againſt him. There is none that converſt with them but can teſtify to the Truth of this, and I doubt not but this Author had his ſhare in it. Nay, may we not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how highly many of them reſented King <hi>Charles</hi> II. His par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning the late Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> and could not forbear ſaying, <hi>What! has His Majeſty ſerved us thus?</hi> So that we may ſee that either they muſt be above the King and have him at their beck, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will ſatisfy them: And notwithſtanding all our Author has ſaid
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98001:15"/>in his Parties Vindication, that ſaying of the Father of lies will be a Truth when applyed to them, <hi>viz. Does</hi> Job <hi>ſerve God for nought?</hi> For if they be but diſ-ſatisfied in the leaſt none would curſe the King more than they would do.</p>
            <p>As for what he ſays, that <hi>the Doctrine cannot be unſeaſonable, ſince no Governm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt can be ſafe without it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 2.</note> it is manifeſtly falſe; for if a King keeps himſelf within the due bounds that God and the Laws of the Land ſet him, he needs not fear any hurt from his Subjects, tho' there were not a Man in the world that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Non-reſiſtance. And on the other hand, if this Principle were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally maintained, I would fain know how the World could be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from Tyranny and all manner of Oppreſſion and Injuſtice. I hope this Author will acknowledge that we muſt not always expect Miracles. Now were this Doctrine generally held, we could never he ſafe but under good Princes, and ſcarce under them, could but ſuch Gentlemen as this Author get the Aſcendant over them, and if we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe Hiſtories of former times, we ſhall find ſeveral bad Kings to one Good. Now if this Doctrine were become Univerſal, there would be no reſtrain upon a King, the Laws would prove but like <hi>Samſons</hi> Cords, which he without fear would ſnap aſunder at his pleaſure, ſince he knew that whatever he did all would be patiently taken. May we not then juſtly apply that of our Saviour to the Phariſees, to thoſe men that advance ſuch dangerous Opinions, <hi>That they would bind heavy Burdens on other Mens Shoulders, but would not touch them with one of their little Fingers?</hi> And put the ſame Queſtion to them which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle did to Judaizing Chriſtians, <hi>Acts.</hi> 15.10. <hi>Why tempt you God to put a Yoke upon the Neck of the Diſciples, which neither we nor our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were able to bear?</hi> And is there any Yoke more grievous than, that People and Nations muſt be all their life long in Bondage, and that without any hopes of Redreſs, except by a Miracle? Did not the wiſeſt of Men and Princes ſay, <hi>Oppreſſion maketh a wiſe man mad?</hi> But to apply this Doctrine to our Conſtitution here, would not this Doctrine at one blow cut off all the Rights of Parliament? And then we ſhould have no Laws but the Kings Pleaſure; For were this Doctrine in force, he might lay on a Tax at his pleaſure, and ſend out Booted Apoſtles to force the People to pay whatever the impoſed upon them, and if they would not pay it willingly, take it perforce from them, and all the while they muſt patiently ſit ſtill, and not make the leaſt Oppoſition againſt thoſe that are ſent out by him, whatever Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages they ſhould commit. And is not this a Doctrine highly advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98001:15"/>to Humane Societies? I am afraid our Author and his party were they touched in the quick with this would be as ready to kick as thoſe men they ſo much rail at. But we may generally obſerve that the greateſt Cowards boaſt moſt of their Courage, before it come to be tryed in Battel, and therefore we ſhall excuſe them for once.</p>
            <p>As for his Inſtance of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. Tho' there is no good Man but abhors the barbarous Murdering of that Prince,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> yet I think our Author cannot but acknowledge, that he, tho' of a very good nature, was drawn aſide (no doubt by ſuch Gentlemen as he) to act ſeveral Illegal things. It is certainly known that the Maſſacre in <hi>Ireland</hi> did ſtir up the Spirits of many in <hi>England,</hi> out of a fear leſt they ſhould ſuffer the ſame things here; and the advice of ſome high flown men given to that King, of introducing new Ceremonies into the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſtirred up the Spirits of that Kingdom; all which jumping together made way to his ruine: Which was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards effected by ſome bloody, ſelf-deſigning men that made a party in the Army. But our Author needs not wonder ſo much as he does to ſee her Sons diſown that which he calls her Doctrine, ſince he might have known that many of her Sons were in the Parliament Army (a great part of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. Army being Roman Catholicks, ſo that they were but the ſmalleſt Number of the Church of <hi>England</hi> that joyned him.) But as I ſaid, before this Gentleman reckons none true Sons of the Church but thoſe of his own ſize; As for the reſt, I doubt not but he includes them with thoſe <hi>Enemies, who make a faſting day of our Saviours Nativity (as if they were ſorry that he came into the World, and perhaps with reaſon, becauſe their Actions were ſo contrary, both to his Precepts and Example.</hi>) By which we may ſee that this Gentleman has been ſo intent in conning the 13 of the <hi>Romans,</hi> that he had no time to ſpare for the 14th. Otherwiſe he would have been more ſparing in raſh judging, for he might have read in Verſe 4 of that Chapter. <hi>Let not him that eateth deſpiſe him that eateth not let not him that eateth not, diſpiſe him that eateth</hi>—and in v. 6. <hi>He that keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a day to the Lord be keepeth it; and he that keepeth not a day to the Lord he keepeth it not.</hi> — Or it may be our Author has paſt his courſes of ſmaller Duties, ſuch as this is, and minds only the Topping and moſt difficult, ſuch as Non reſiſtance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſo the old Proverb may be applied to him, <hi>Aquila non captat muſcas.</hi> But I muſt take the Liberty to tell him, that the Generality of our high Non-reſiſtance mens practice is as contrary to the Precepts and Example of our Lord, as the worſt of thoſe that (he ſays) make a faſting day for our Saviours Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:98001:16"/>
            <p>He tells us next, <hi>Did we ſeriouſly ſtudy the Laws of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and conſider the Indiſpenſable Obligations laid on us of taking up the Croſs, &amp;c.</hi> Very true, but becauſe we are ordered to take up the Croſs when called to it, muſt we therefore make one for our ſelves, as if we were as ambitious of it as the Primitive Chriſtians were of Martyrdom. I think our Author himſelf, if he be of that Church he profeſſes, will not therefore juſtifie the Papiſts making a Rod to chaſtiſe themſelves with on good <hi>Friday,</hi> or think that God is pleaſed therewith, ſince he never deſired them to take up that Croſs: many croſſes are laid upon us by God, which yet we may uſe lawful means to get rid of particularly ſickneſs; and he would be thought a fool that would not apply himſelf to Phyſicians to get free of it, but would expect to be cured by a Miracle: And till our Author has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven better Arguments for Non-reſiſtance than we have yet ſeen, we muſt take the Liberty to ſay, that in order to the preſerving of our Lives againſt a Tyrant that would take them away, we may as war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantably make uſe of Self-Defence, as of Phyſicians when ſickneſs threatens us with Death.</p>
            <p>His Inſtance of the Gnoſticks is very far from the purpoſe, for as the Author he quotes upon that Subject ſays,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> they rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned <hi>all Governments to be nothing elſe but the contrivance of ſome evil Spirits,</hi> whereas there are none of thoſe that are for Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence (if we except thoſe of the Fifth Monarchy Principle) but have as great a veneration for Government as any of his Party, and would hazard as much for the ſupporting thereof as any of them; but as for Tyranny, when people are much in the ſame caſe, if not worſe, than if there were no Government at all, the caſe is quite altered. That other Citation of <hi>Machiavel</hi> is much to the ſame purpoſe, and therefore I paſs it.</p>
            <p>He next reflects upon <hi>Hobbs,</hi> (but I ſuppoſe deſigned to wound another through his ſides,<note place="margin">Page 4.</note> for in other points I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they needed no Reconciliation) and his Conſcience is mightily ſtartled (if he has any) at the dangerous Tenets which he revived, <hi>viz. That Power is originally in the people, that the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Government is laid in Compact, and that the Breach of Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by one Party juſtifies that of the other.</hi> But I would gladly hear his Proofs that Power was not Originally in the people; and how Kings came firſt by their Power: For all that ever this Author or any of his party have ſaid about it is a meer <hi>Chimaera, viz.</hi> That Kings as they derived their Lives, ſo they received their Power from <hi>Adam</hi> and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98001:16"/>
               <hi>Noah,</hi> by virtue of their Primogeniture, as the firſt had it immediately from God, without any conſent of the People: But firſt, then it would follow that Mankind ſhould be born as great ſlaves as Beaſts, ſince a King in ſuch a caſe ſhould have as much Propriety over them, as any Countrey-man has over his Horſe, Cows or Sheep; than which nothing can be more repugnant to reaſon. 2. It would follow that there ſhould have been but one Univerſal King over the whole Earth, <hi>viz.</hi> the Eldeſt Son of <hi>Noah,</hi> who undoubtedly muſt have that Power over all his Younger Brethren, and conſequently his Poſterity in the right line, muſt have had the ſame Power over their Poſterity, and there could not have been any other Kings unleſs he or his Poſterity in the right line had made them their Vicegerents; but this is altogether Inhiſtorical: And therefore their poſition muſt be falſe. For it is certain that the great Monarchies that have been in the World were but ſmall Kingdoms at the firſt, and that for a conſiderable time, and were afterward enlarged by Conqueſt. 3. If this Conjecture had been true; it would follow that God himſelf contradicted his own Order, without any reaſon for it: For upon the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> deſiring a King, ſhould not he rather have made choice of the chief of the firſt Tribe, than of one of the meaneſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of the Youngeſt Tribe, <hi>viz. Saul,</hi> who was not maſter of ſuch Vertues as to recommend him to the Crown before all the reſt of the Children of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> The like may be ſaid of <hi>David</hi> who was not of the Eldeſt Family of <hi>Judah;</hi> and tho' he was a Man after Gods own heart, yet according to thoſe Gentlemens opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, another ſhould not have been deprived of his Right. And ſince this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion has not the leaſt ground for it, it muſt neceſſarily follow that it was by E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, and conſequently that the Power of Election reſided in the People; and as the People did elect them, ſo it is moſt rational to ſuppoſe, that Articles were drawn up betwixt them and the People, which were to be mutually obſerved; for 'tis very improbable that People would give up themſelves as Bondſlaves to that Prince, but entruſted him with the Government meerly that they might under him lead quiet and peaceable Lives; and ſince he had no right to Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize over People, his Succeſſors could have no more right than he, and if he or they did endeavour to oppreſs the Subjects, &amp; encroach upon their Liberties and Priviledges, they might lawfully defend themſelves. But this Subject is too large to inſiſt upon, and therefore I muſt leave it, tho' in our Gentlemans opinion one of the Fundamental Points of Chriſtianity!</p>
            <p>Another Damnable Doctrine that makes this good Mans hairs ſtand an end is, <hi>That when Religion is a part of our Property it may be defended.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> But why ſhould this be ſuch a Bugbear? For what has been more dear to all Nations in the World than Religion? If Civil Priviledges may be maintained, and if we enjoy as them helps to us in our Religion, or ſerving God, then it will follow, that we may much more maintain our religious Priviledges. Nothing can be more dear or more worth the preſerving in a Land than the freedom of our Religion: Has not the Scripture it ſelf reckoned it the greateſt of Priviledges when it ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed are they that hear the Joyful ſound?</hi> And if it be ſuch a Mercy, may we not at leaſt uſe all the means for maintaining of it that we may do for a Mercy of an Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Nature? But I would fain know if a King ſhould go about to put down the Hierarchy and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> what our Author and his Party would do, whether or no they would defend their Religion: He that would think they would patiently ſit with it, would I doubt not be mightily miſtaken: Nay have we not ſufficiently ſeen of late what they would do, by the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98001:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>practice of their Brethren in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and their publick Approbation of it here in moſt Coffee-houſes? For none have been ſo Induſtrious of late (and that with a miſchievous Deſign to ſtir up people againſt the Government) as thoſe very Men, in buzzing it about here that the turning out of the Biſhops in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was the only occaſion of <hi>Dundee's</hi> Rebellion there. And why have ſo many of them Vindicated them for ſo doing? Of all men of the World it leaſt became them; &amp; had they conſidered how contradictory that behaviour is to the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance, they would have had more prudence whatever they thought, than to have ſaid ſo. So that by this we may ſee however Heterodox this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is, <hi>That Religion when it is a part of our Property may be defended,</hi> yet thoſe Gentlemen would maintain it when it makes for their Turn.</p>
            <p>He concludes this Paragraph with telling you, that he <hi>ſpeaks this God knows to confute the Calumny,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 5.</note> 
               <hi>and with the deepeſt ſence of the Intereſts of a poor deſpiſed Church, which is ſtill and will be the beſt, the moſt Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, and moſt Primitive of all Chriſtendom</hi> Magiſterially ſpoken! But why deſpiſed? I know no Man deſpiſes her; but it would ſeem our Author by his deſpiſed Church means only thoſe perſons that have refuſed to take the Oaths: And it is no wonder if that party of it be deſpiſed, that out of a humour or ſome ſiniſter Arbitrary deſign, advance ſuch Doctrines in the World as have ſuch a tendency to the enſlaving and Oppreſſion of Mankind in General. But this Gentleman talks more like a Son of Infallibility, than one that acknowledges a Church to be fallible: For why ſhould he thus extol the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſo highly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all other Churches: That ſhe is a famous Church none will deny, and alſo that ſhe has as Learned and Pious men in her Communion as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church: But it is always a ſign both of Prudence and Modeſty not to run out too much in our own Praiſe: The Proverb holds ſtill <hi>Laus proprio fordeſcit in ore,</hi> I could wiſh it were more minded by thoſe men, when they thus claim to themſelves an Excellence beyond all other Churches. This more becomes a Church that pretends to Infallibility than any other. We have heard of a Church that ſaid ſhe was rich and well clothed, and ſtood in need of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, when yet ſhe wanted every thing: I do not ſay this as If I thought that her caſe were the ſame with that of that Church, but only that ſhe and every other Church ſhould not think of themſelves ſo as to deſpiſe all others. But he not only ſays that ſhe <hi>is,</hi> but that ſhe <hi>will</hi> be, which yet ſavours more of Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libity: Could our Author ſpare ſo much time from reading thoſe places in the Scripture which he thinks make moſt for Non-reſiſtance, I would deſire him to read the ſecond and third Chapter of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and there he would find that the Seven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> (which the Spirit of God called the <hi>Seven Golden Candleſticks</hi>) were once as famous Churches as ever the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or any other Church was, and yet many years ago there has been little reſemblance of a Church there. And the ſame may befal her or any other Church: But if it do not, I am ſure ſhe need not thank this Author or any of his Party for it; for could they bring about their deſigns, ſhe would quickly be brought to that paſs, when we had the Romiſh Crew again brought in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us.</p>
            <p>That Citation he quotes out of <hi>Creſſy</hi> is as little to his purpoſe, and he mentions it only to make us believe that Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> and other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants abroad were Champions for Non-reſiſtance;<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> but if ſo, how came ſo many Pulpits to thunder out againſt <hi>Calvin</hi> and other Foreign Proteſtants as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98001:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Broachers of Sedition? And why were ſeveral of their Works burnt at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, An.</hi> 1683. when Non-reſiſtance was culminant? However it ſeems he is a very good-natured Gentleman, and would make Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſome redreſs for the Injury that has been done to his Reputation.</p>
            <p>But to let you know the ſincerity of his Undertaking, he tells you that he <hi>intends no Diſturbance by it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>ſince he only does the Office of an Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> in barely citing his Authors, and ſo he excuſes himſelf from making good every Argument therein, ſince the Authors moſt of them being alive, are obliged to manage that; wherein he is to be commended for his Prudence, for I am afraid it would have been too difficult a Task for him: But I thought that the Evidence of Scripture and Reaſon was to be a Proteſtants Rule, and not blindly to believe as the Church or generality of her Fathers believe: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would have done much more for his Cauſe, had he himſelf demonſtrated the Neceſſity of Non-reſiſtance by ſolid Arguments taken from Scripture and Reaſon, and the univerſal practice of all ſober men, than by thus ſetting down a multitude (of it may be not a few of them wreſted) expreſſions of ſeveral Learned Men. But his deſign is no leſs than, ſince he ſees that he and his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cannot carry on their miſchievous purpoſes, to ſtir up and exaſperate the minds of ſimple inconſiderate people againſt thoſe Learned Men. For all men of conſideration muſt acknowledge, that the beſt and moſt Learned Men are not exempted from Errors, as alſo that there is ſcarce any man ſo even temper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that ſometimes Paſſion and Prejudice againſt a Party may carry them out too far in a prepoſterous Zeal, ſo as to utter not only many unbecoming ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions againſt the Opinions of a Party they have a diſlike at, but even to run too far upon the extream. And this is no new thing in the World. But that thoſe Learned Men have remitted of that heighth of Loyalty, which they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at the times when they publiſhed thoſe ſayings which he quotes, ſeems to me clear from this: That ſince the Reſtauration of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. that ſubject was moſtly inſiſted on (and that chiefly, as I believe, from a deteſtation of the Barbarous Murder of King <hi>Charles</hi> I.) and eſpecially towards the latter end of his Reign, and the beginning of the late King <hi>James</hi>'s, when yet there was not half the danger of its being tranſgreſt, (by thoſe of the Communion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> at leaſt) as towards the latter end of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, when the generality of the Church of <hi>England</hi> was diſcontented; and yet then, when it was in moſt danger to be laid aſide, eſpecially about the time when His Preſent Majeſty was Undertaking his Expedition for our Delivery, it was not in the leaſt inſiſted on any where that I could hear of; which if it had been ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually done, and people practiſed accordingly, who doubts but we had been in worſe Circumſtances than ever? For the Army that was brought over could have ſignified nothing againſt King <hi>James</hi>'s, had not (to give them our Authors denomination) ſo many Rebellious Subjects joined them. Now I can ſee no other reaſon why they did not inſiſt on it then, but that they ſaw the evil of running out too much upon it formerly, and conſidered that if they ſhould ſlight ſo favourable a Providence as God had offered, for delivering them from Popery and Slavery, they ſhould juſtly have forfeited all ſhare of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of God, when their deſtruction would have been ſo manifeſtly of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and incurred the juſt hatred and indignation of all Proteſtants abroad, whoſe ſecurity depended upon theirs, and the deriſion even of Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And what reaſonable Man will condemn them for renouncing a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98001:18"/>which if they had at that time retained it, would have ruined Three Kingdoms?</p>
            <p>To conclude, ſince what follows of his Preface is much the ſame with what has been taken notice of above, I ſhall paſs it. Any underſtanding Reader may eaſily ſmell out the deſign of it, as alſo of publiſhing the Declaration of a late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceaſed Prelate, the publiſhers whereof ſeem to have had little reſpect to his credit, when they expoſed what he wrote in his weakneſs to publick cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. But I am very far miſtaken if it carry any more weight in it than the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words of ſome of the <hi>Cameronian</hi> party in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſince his Reaſons he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces for it have no greater ſtrength than theirs had, and they died with as much comfort as he, and which is more, died actually for that which they gave Teſtimony to, which he did not, tho it's true he was ſuſpended for it: But grant he had died for it, yet ſhould we embrace every Opinion, upon our ſeeing ſome dye for it, we ſhould change as many Opinions as there are points in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the great Argument they inſiſt upon is, that ſince they have Sworn Allegiance to the late King, they cannot Swear to any other during his Life, if ſome do not go further, <hi>viz.</hi> the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales</hi>'s, and whither that would tend, the Reader may judge: I ſhall only adduce one Inſtance out of Scripture, that ſeems to come pretty near our caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that when <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> took <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and made <hi>Zedekiah</hi> his Priſoner, tho' that King was of a different Religion and Foreign Nation, (which was of great weight among the Jews,) yet all the honeſt Men of the Jewiſh Nation owned his Authority, and were juſtified by the Scripture for ſo doing: Tho' there was a Party of them that would not (ſet on work by the King of the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> who deſigned no leſs in it, than the utter deſtruction of that People; as we know a Neighbouring Tyrant, that is and has been no leſs active in ſtirring up People here, with the ſame deſign as that King did then) yet we ſee from <hi>Jer.</hi> 42. what ſort of Men they were. And tho' I doubt not but ſome of thoſe that refuſe to take the Oaths do it in the ſincerity of their Soul, yet it is too plain that there are too many of the ſame ſort of men amongſt the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. But I hope that all true hearted <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> and good Proteſtants <hi>will in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> their day know the things that belong to their Peace, before they be hid from their Eyes,</hi> and as they have hither to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared for their Religious and Civil Liberties in devolving the Government up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their preſent Majeſties; ſo they will concur with them in ſetting the three Kingdoms, and endeavour to bring to exemplary puniſhment all ſuch as diſturb the Peace of our <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS,</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
